<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sarmon, of Ihon Oecolampadius, to yong men, and maydens</title>
            <author>Oecolampadius, Johann, 1482-1531.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104178</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839917</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839917</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4378</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08463)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4378)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 121:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sarmon, of Ihon Oecolampadius, to yong men, and maydens</title>
                  <author>Oecolampadius, Johann, 1482-1531.</author>
                  <author>Foxe, John, 1516-1587.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By me Humfrey Powell, dwellyng aboue Holburne conduit. And are to be sould by Hugh Syngleton, dwellyng at the sygne of Saint Augustine, in Poules church yarde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated by John Foxe.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C (C8 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4378:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4378:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>A<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> ☞ Sarmon, ☜ of Ihon Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lampadius, to yong men, and maydens. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="to_the_translator">
            <pb facs="tcp:4378:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4378:2"/>
            <head>To his harty freind Maſter ſegraue Iohn Foxe the tranſlatour, whyſhyth grace and lyght of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit.</head>
            <p>Sythen the tyme I fyrſt perceiued in you, your deſire to the word of God and hys holy inſtitution, I haue not ceaſed to be ſollycytus in mynd and prayers for you, deſiring the father and ſender of our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Chryſt to encreaſe that thing in you whyche he hath begone. And that inwardly you myght be reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed wyth plentuous ſpyryt and knowledge of the great glory and ryches, which is geuen vs in Chriſt to thentent you myght be altered in the ſence of your mind to a new ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, And profeſly forſak the vaine frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thys earthly world, and to embrace y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorious vocatyon whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:4378:3"/>
we called to in chriſte. The whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I thynk is hard for you and us all to do. The ſence of our fleſhe is ſo ſtrong. The temptyng ſpyrytt is ſo ready. Neuertheleſſe inſomuche yet it is our partes wyth mutuall conferring one to exhorte an other. And alſo for the brotherly affection I beare to you warde, I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not nor aught not I ſuppoſe, but ſome thyng I ſay as concernyng your ſpyrytuall eadyfycation. And by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe yow ſhall not take my exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyones whyche be but of feble weyght, for you to ſtyk vnto, here I haue traunſlated and ſent to you a fruitfull adhortacion of a famoſe Chryſtiane I, Oecola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>padius, deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng you to accepte well in worthe thys labore beſtowed, and alſo to geue dilygent reding to his precep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis whoſe inſtitutions yf you wyll attently mark and peruſe, I doubt
<pb facs="tcp:4378:3"/>
nothyng, but you ſhall receyue no ſmale fruyte thereatt, beyng ſuffycyently inſtructed in all thynges you ſhall deſire. The liuing grace of chryſt be with you. So be it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4378:4"/>
            <p>Thys thing which I ſhall ſpeake here to young mene whiche muſt be fede fyrſt wyth mylke and ſuch tender meat, I wold lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe yow that be elders and more auncyente in chryſtes doctryne, to practyſe the ſame dylygently, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man in hys owne houſe at home, for lytyll yt ſhal avayle thus open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to preache vnto you, vnlſſe ye vſe the ſame in your houſholdes, the whyche pryuat and domeſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call inſtructyone I thynke ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytable and neceſſarye in chryſtes churche, that wythout yt our open ſermones though they be neuer ſo good and learneyd ſhall lytell ſynke or remane in younge men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hartes, by reaſone theyr myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and ſenſes be ſo wanderynge and ſet vpon tryffles ratheyr than to marke anye good thynge, ſuche thynges as be holſome and for ther
<pb facs="tcp:4378:4"/>
ſoules healthe fewe of theme rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde vnleſſe they be broughte vp frome theyre youth in the feare of god. To you now there fore young men, I ſpeake that be chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened. Your parentes whethere they be alyue or deade, brought you of a good and a chryſtene mynde to be chryſtenede, that ye myght be dead frome thys world and ſynne. Remembre wherfore god dyd call you to that lyfe not that you ſhuld liue here and hepe vp riches in this world, but that you ſhould inheryte the kyngdome of heauen. The whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che kyngdome ſhalbe geuen only to them that feare god, &amp; worke righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tueſnes, yf we lyue wyckedly and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue in ſynnes, ſo as the faſhion of yonge menne and maides is to doo, perpetuall damnatione and fyer euerlaſtynge ſhall folwe, for god is a iuſt iudge. Agaynne yf we
<pb facs="tcp:4378:5"/>
wyll walke in the commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the Lorde we ſhall fynde ioy and lyffe euerlaſtynge, in heauen withe the Aungelles and all godly ſaynctes. But yf you wyll not ceaſſe from your ſinnes &amp; wickednes but ſtill remayne and wallowe in your noughttynes, loke for nothynge els but euerlaſtynge fyer withe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil. You yong perſons you be bound to be obedyent to your Parentes in all thynges ſaue onely ſuch as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynes to god and your ſoule ward, in all other matters yf you lyue not obedyent to them, ye haue no excuſe before god the fyrſte and pryncypal honor muſte be to god, the next af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to our parentes what profyt is it, yf thy parentes do tender the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo much, make the ther heire of all they haue, and pamper the vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all maner of delycates. And thow to loſe the fauore of God, with out
<pb facs="tcp:4378:5"/>
the which, there is no health no quietnes, euen as though a man for one lyttell peace of lande full of wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and bryers, ſhuld for ſake all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole ryches and treaſure of the world. And at lenght the lord ſhall alſo fynde theſe out whan he ſhall iudge the worlde. All yought for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part folow the commen ſort of people hauing no dyfferenc betwixt good and badde, and other not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng thynges ſprytuall, or els not regardynge them, fyrſte loke ye be obedyent to the word of God, and harken to yt dayly and dylygently. And if your pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes do grug their<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with or be offended, do you rather feare and regard your heauenli fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which hath both power of bodi &amp; ſoule, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your fleſhli pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che haue no pouer ouer you but onli inwardli thinges whiche is rather then to be eſteymed, God whyche is
<pb facs="tcp:4378:6"/>
almyghty &amp; whyche hath promyſed heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or your pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes here whyche geue you but earthly thynges and ſuche as be tranſſitory &amp; caſual to euery blaſte of fortu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, Truly god I knowe vndoubted ſome pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che do all they can that there chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſhuld not heare the worde of God, O foules and peruerſe people, vnworthe to be named chryſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt nedes here in this world haue ſome god to ſerue, otheyr the god of heauen or els the deuyll the great aduerſary of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynd, it muſt nedes folow, for ſo ſayth chryſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerue two lordes at ons. Thei whyche wyll not ſerue god, do ſerue the deuyl, &amp; be all the minyſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil which do not lede a chryſtiane lyfe, And for thys cauſe chryſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens chyldren wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be chriſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned be told to abrenounce al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil, and ſo they promyſe
<pb facs="tcp:4378:6"/>
here after if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liue, to lead a chriſtie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> life to folow what ſo euer Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeith to eſchue what ſo euer god forbideth. And this voue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth god right well. Periured and for ſworune you be yf ye break your voue, ſay not now. I made no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe at my baptyme. Thy parents &amp; thy god fatheres promyſed in thy be halfe, whome alſo here I charge and warne, that thys voue be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formede and dyſcharged. It hath bene taken for an heygh matter of godlynes yf a yong man had voued him ſelfe into ſome moneſteri there to remayne in ſeruice of God &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall pouerti. but vnleſe they had bene entyced in with promyſys and fayere flattery wordes, they wold neuer haue concented to that wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked madnes, to bynd them ſelues in abbayes, where as was nothyng leſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſeruice of god excerciſed.
<pb facs="tcp:4378:7"/>
Now for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part of yought they nether knowe what god, what the deuell, what good, or what euell meanes. Nether is god nor the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill ani ſuch thyng as the painters make them. Yf you know how mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull god is how good, how meke. how gentyll, how ſufferynge, howe pacyent and iuſte he is? than you know god, for by thes propertes we lerne what god is. Contrarywyſe, the deuyll is nothyng els but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercyfulnes, hattred, enuy, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, lying, mockyng of our neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and al thyng that is nought, forthermore they be the chyldren of god whyche folow god in vertu in innocency, mercy, pety, and vnfey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned charite. Againe thei be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the deuyll, whyche be lying, cruell, vnmercyfull, dyſobedyent to their parentes, periured. Thei whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be obedyent to god, doo all ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:4378:7"/>
as pleaſe god. They that ſerue the deuyll, doo that pleaſe hym. Wylt thou now ſerue god, then ſett thyne eys of thy mind and marke chryſte, be iuſt, gentyl, meke true, faythfull. Thow haſt abrenounced all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the deuyll in thy baptyſme, now what be the workes of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl, I ſhal bryuely declare. To bak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byte and ſpeak yll of men, to moke, to dyſpyſe, to ſcoffe at widews and aged me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to geue no reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to thy parentes, and chefly to neglect the worde of god, and to blaſphem hys name, wordly men loue to go pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſly arayde, wyth ther hoſſe Iag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> play &amp; make mery as thowgh they ſhuld euermore lyue, &amp; neuer peryſh, they ryot and reuell they vſe moſt impudent danſces, they go vp and doune from one ſtreat to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the nyght long wyth theyr crying &amp; routtyng they take away
<pb facs="tcp:4378:8"/>
from aged me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and infyrme perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s their naturall reſte and quietnes. They lytell regard there parentes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, what ſo euer they ſpeke vnto them, they make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yght an a moke at yt, yea &amp; that is worſſe the greatter forte of them can not ſay the Lordes praier right, and yf they can ſay the wordes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrynght and ſprit therof thei haue not. They bable vp ther praiers as the nounes were wount to do theyr pſalter. But ſuch yong men as ſerue and add yet themſelues to chryſt be not polluted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch manner of wickednes. Then ſuch lewed and wicked perſons wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ych leade there tyme ſo abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, let them nothing hynder you in your vertuous doyngs, wether thei be preeſtis or lay me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or what ſo euer they be, for the pompe and pryde of thys world, yet neuer pleaſed God. nor neuer ſhall. And yet it is plaine
<pb facs="tcp:4378:8"/>
ſuch thynges do greatly delyte and ſturre vp yong me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as haue not yet learned to folow reaſon nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyder the ende and death of man. Yt is nothyng els all thys but vanyte, to paſtyme, to ſport, to dryncke, to feight, to ſet idle, to ſolace. O Lord how petifully is our youth brought vp, euen from there chyld age. wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfore when they cum to be men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde ther fruites appere ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. In like as our firſt parentes in paradyce a place of all pleaſure, were forbid from thaple, that aboue all thinge thei ſhuld be ware and be circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpectid therin. But after that through the deueles inſtigatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had committid in takyng of thaple, they fell into all maner of myſerys, where with we be all now oppreſſed to thys day. Euen ſo lykewyſe, it is now amongeſt youth which ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Glory of thys worlde to be nothinge elles but all
<pb facs="tcp:4378:9"/>
pleaſure and delite and all together honei, whan in dede it is bitter poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and verili euerlaſting da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I do not here ſpeke agaynſt honeſte myrth and ſuch maner of excerſyce of the body as be cumly. But bica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe I perceaue the deuell thus to go about with ſuch delytes and baytes to ſnare yong me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and maides, and ſo to ſeduce them frome all goodnes yf they wyll conſent vnto hym that at leynght he makyth them cleane deſperat, bothe with out all feare of god and all ſhamfaſtenes. which is the onely ornament of all yong age in ſo much that nether they regard god, nether truthe, nor iuſtice, good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes nor honeſty nor no other vertu wherof alſo proceideth there grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dyſtruction that they wyll not harken to the word of god, nor be not brought vnto yt by ther pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. O you parentes litell do you know
<pb facs="tcp:4378:9"/>
what a charg lieth apo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your backes. And you chyldren, whan wyll you remembre and conſyder what yt is, you promyſed to god in your bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſme? Yt is not to be neglected, I tell you, that you voue &amp; promyſſe vnto god? he requireth our fayth, &amp; ſuche vnfaithfull falſe couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keres he wyll punyſh and that moſt ſharpely. The lorde ſetyth before vs tow wayes, the one, to lyfe, the other to dyſtrucſyon. Marke nowe well ye chyldren of the lorde. The one is ſharp thornie &amp; full of briers, which few men do walke, but after that yt be entred ones, yt ys very playne and pleaſant &amp; bryngeth to euerlaiſting life. The other ſemeth fyrſte delectable, as though it ſhuld co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducte vs to all maner of goodnes, but at leyngeh and laſt ende, yt caſtith vs head loung doune to hell, where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuill and all his au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles
<pb facs="tcp:4378:10"/>
be kepte faſte abydyng the daye and iudgment of god. Therfore ſaythe Chriſt. Mathew vii. Enter in be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtraeyt wycket, for brode is the way that leadeth to perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and large is the dore and many enter in ther at. And agayne ſtrayet is the dore and the way narrow which leadeth into heauen, and fewe there be that fynde it. The lyfe of all true chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans foloweth thys ſtrayet waye, in the which waye they be daily excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed and tourmoyled in perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyones of thys worlde, And they ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer ceaſe nor reſt, to they haue fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed there courſe and come where thei wold be. Say ſome. Then ſhall I not kepe company with my fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes and aquaintance, ſhall I not make mery with my goſſeptes and ſolace w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ones or twiſe a wicke?</p>
            <p>I am no mounke nor fryer. what man is able to kepe ſo ſtraite a rule,
<pb facs="tcp:4378:10"/>
you muſt conſyder we be men, what wold you we ſhuld do? here my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, good ſonne, what thou ſhalt do, for I know what the world is wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to abiect and ſaye, here, I ſay, and obaye the word of god. And vndoub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted thou ſhall ſone perceyue thys ſtrayte waye now to thy ſeauynge, ſhortely to be eaſy and pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And I do not doubt but at leynght thou ſhall gyue me great thankes for my counſell, whiche haue kepte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frmoe ſuche dyſtruction and ieoperdy. I wold wyſh to all you yong men and children, the eyes of your mind ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ye myght ſee the ende that ſuch men come to, One is ſlane beynge droncke and madde, an other hath his arme or legg ſtroke of, an other goyth a robbynge &amp; feyght wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully for other mens money and ſo ſtroke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and ſlayne lyke a beſte, An other is hangged for a ſmalle
<pb facs="tcp:4378:11"/>
tryfle. And who can recyte vp all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyndes of death and diſttructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſuch dyſobedyent perſons as theſe come vnto? what nede we any example to be brought whan dayly experyence declareth what ende &amp; miſchef theſe wretches com to. And the ſame I ſpeke alſo to yong weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and maydes. They be wanton and incontynent they haue and drawe to ſuch felowes after their owone ſort more lecherous than any gote, they ſcoffe &amp; moke euery yong mane that cometh by them, they delyte. moſt in baudi ſonges. Some labore and bryngeth forth pryuely, and ſo they turne other to be common ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes or eles be dryuen to extreme pouertie, and ſo liue in contempte and miſeri all their life long. What honeſt yong man wold be copled or content to be ioyned in maryage w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch a beaſte? Then what coſte of
<pb facs="tcp:4378:11"/>
aparel haue thei y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt baſſe &amp; beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerli weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which haue right nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght yet how ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuouſly they muſte go arayed, Amongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very gentyls a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal not find more exceſſe and pryde in veſture, wherfore learne be tyme you Chryſten yonglynges to feare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde god. And with hole harte &amp; mynde harken to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of hym euery mornyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ye do, and euery ſonday. And let it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng perturbe you, though ye be gruged or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned therfore for the ſeruyce of god, for thys it ys y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth god moſt heighli, it is no mater whether we lyue or dye to the lorde, that is ynoughe for vs, what ſhuld paſſe for more? And thinke this ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſtudy how you may folow hym. And care not for thys vayne ſort of men thys raſcall rable of ruf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feynns whiche can nothyng els but eate and playe &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſtreyts
<pb facs="tcp:4378:12"/>
to be ſene of other. And the ſame I ſpeke to yong maydes lykewyſe, yf god ſend vs long lyfe here, and we ſpend it i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tones, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhall be caſt into perpetuall fier. Hyere my in hys lamentationes .iii. ſayth, it is good for a man if he bere his yoke i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his youth. And good it is for a man yf he teach hys ſoule in hys youth to beare the yocke of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des commaundementes, if we wyll be contente to ſerue god, then ſhall the ſee &amp; tempeſt of our tentations ſoone ſwage, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde wyll neuer forſake vs. Thei which be elder me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and haue receued light of god i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his goſpell, know what I ſai, &amp; greatly complayne ther myſery and ingno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in which they haue bene brou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght vp and led. Oh (ſaye they) yf we hadde harde ſuch knowledge in the ſcripture which now we here, than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be to god, we wold neuer haue
<pb facs="tcp:4378:12"/>
runned in the anger of god as we haue. Yong age maie be wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to tendre graftes or buddes apte to be bended which waye you wyll, yf ye take them in time and while thei be tendre, but yf they be ons grouen and paſte in bignes, it is but loſte labor what ſo euer ye do, breake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhal ſonner than bend them, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they be come to there nature. The ſame thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g we ſee likwiſe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brute beaſtes. Take me a lyon and bring hym vp amongeſt men, he wyll be tame. And lyke yt ys with children, yll education and bryngyng vp ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth much in marring a man. filthe wordes and baudy talke is agreate token of a corrupte harte. You muſt take better hede than ye haue done yet, what company your chyldren kepe, what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munycation they vſe, &amp; this ſhal make you chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people. children be as much conſecrated to
<pb facs="tcp:4378:13"/>
god, as though they were a nointed preeſtes, or ſhauen into any order of relygyon. Conſyder groundly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy ſelfe and tremble, yf thou be in the anger of god, canſte thou ſlepe quyetly or take any reſte? Yt wyll vexe an honeſt man yf hys neybour beare hym dyſpleaſure. And a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll chyld yf he ſee hys father ſore angred with hym, he can not tell what to do to a voide his diſpleaſur with flatteryng, with wepyng he aſſayeth all wayes he can to be reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyled a gayne vnto his father. Then how much more owght we to proue all meanes we maye, to be reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled to our heauenly father, whome we haue offended ſo oft euery howere, whiche hath bothe geuen vs oure body and ſoule. They be but tryfles that our fatheres beſtowe apon vs in comparyſon to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we receue of god. The lorde our father ones
<pb facs="tcp:4378:13"/>
plaged the world with the floode of waters, onely reſeruynge eyght perſonnes, whome he preſeruede from the waters through hys mere grace only. Sodome and Gomore with many cyties moo he dyſtroyed with fyer, beſydes what an infinite numbre of men haue bene ſlayne in battayle? who wyll not feare thys lord? he is ſlow to anger, he graunt tyth vs tyme to repente yeares ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycient. He ſendith hys prophets be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to admoniſh vs of his anger to come. Then yf we take no hyed by hys admoniſhments, hys vengance wyll ſtrycke when we leaſte thynke of yt. We know no ende of our lyffe, death crepeth euery day whyle we be moſte in our ruffe, and daylye in our paſtymes. No man hath a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſyon of hys lyfe how longe to lyue. Then why obaye we not the preceptes of god, and ceaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oure
<pb facs="tcp:4378:14"/>
ſinnes which ſlaye the ſoule. Many deceyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues when they ſinne ſecretly, ſuppoſyng that god dothe not beholde them, yf thou ſhuldyſte walke in a deſerte or in the moſt dar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keſte wode where no man could cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the nor ſee the, yet god wolde ſee thy workes. Take hyde of hys ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaunce whiche is ſo ſharpe, for we be redy to offences dyueres, wher w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we greatly prouoke the a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of god. Worke ye the dedes that pleaſe god for theſe two go alwayes together, to ceaſe frome ſinne and to worke charyte. If we ceaſe not from ſinne, we can not worke no goodnes that pleaſeth god. Let vs demaunde our chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus, what fayth profeſeſt thou, doſte thou profeſe that faythe whiche the apoſtolyke church hath left? Tel me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> artycles of thy faith. I beleue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god the father almyghty maker of heauen and earthe. etc.
<pb facs="tcp:4378:14"/>
Let yong men be learned this crede perfectly, and let them ſaye yt not with mouthe. But haue yt in there hartes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may ſet all there truſt a pon God theire maker, that bothe he wyll and alſo is able to defende them. Thys it meanyth, almyghty God is the maker of all thynges of heauen of earth of thynges vyſyble and thynges in viſible. All thynges that be, haue there beyng of god, for with out hym nothynge is made.</p>
            <p>Corne, wyne, oyle, wolle, and all thynges els, yea the Aungelles of heauen. All come of god, here we muſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that all theſe thinges were created for vs.</p>
            <p>Oh what a mercifull father is this, whyche hath ordened ſuch thynges for vs ſo vnworthe wretches?</p>
            <p>what wyll not he graunt vs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, what wyll he denye now to hys chylderen? vnto elder men
<pb facs="tcp:4378:15"/>
and ſuch as be more growne in ther fayth the myſtery of the Trynyte muſt be declared, ſo much as mans weknes may comprehend. There is one god whiche made all thinges, bothe that are in heauen &amp; that are in earth. If thou doſte truſt in god, thou mayſt be ſure the deuill ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not hurte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, much leſe no mortall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. To beleue in god, is to haue a conſtaunte truſte in god, and to driue al thine hope in him, al other thynges and creatures ſet a parte, and that ſhall cauſe vs to loue god truly, other els it ys but a feyned &amp; hypocrytycall loue. It foloueth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crede. And in Ieſus chryſt hys on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne. All mankynde was dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vtterly for their greate and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny folde offences, but chryſte hath borne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Backe all our ſinnes ſatyſfyenge hys father for vs, and deliueri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs from euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g death,
<pb facs="tcp:4378:15"/>
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now we ſhould lyue to our maſter chryſte, who ſoeuer doth inwardly beleue this, wyll conforme hys lyfe honeſtly according to the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of god, eſchuyng all maner of vice, ſo muche as in hym lyeth.</p>
            <p>There is nothyng more abhorrede amongſt true chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyne. Almyghty god fyrſt made Adam &amp; Eue our fyrſt genytoures, and put them in paradyſe, geuyng them an eiſy comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which they tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſſed, deceyued through the ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyltie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl, wherof we al take our ofſprynge. Ye know what they did, and what happened to them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame infection now is gendered in vs. What ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth not ſee thys and proue it daly in hym ſelf, but chefly in childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as we may ſe, this more apereth by lytil &amp; lytil. For they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn to lie, to ſtele, to be light, to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d chekmeat with their pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:4378:16"/>
regarding god, what ſo euer is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, yf we ſe any ſuch vices ſpryng vp in them, we muſt reforme them in tyme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rodes &amp; ſtrypes, leſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil in vale &amp; get the head, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole man ſhal be poyſened w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the venime therof. And ſo they procure to them ſelfes euerlaſting da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, vnleſe they redreſe them ſelues by tyme &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtand ſuch infections while they be freſh &amp; gryne. There is no yonge ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch a babe how yong ſo euer he be, but he can vnderſtand what is good and what is euyll. For this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature writen in all mens hartes, doo to other as thou would be doune to thy ſelf, let vs intermyt nothing in them which become to a more perfect reaſone &amp; vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, that they geue not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the deuyll. Here I admonyſh all childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf you ſe your pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſlack in hearyng the word of god, folow
<pb facs="tcp:4378:16"/>
not their ſteps nor be not lyk them. Al perſons ſhal render a count to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde, &amp; euery man ſhal anſwere for hym ſelf. Deſire to go and heare ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons often, And the lord ſhal geue you plentifull grace to know hym, and ſhal open you a way to all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. The lorde ſhall preſerue you frome all them that contemne hys holy word. Wherfore dyd chryſte dye? to delyuer vs from euerlaſting death. The excedyng great charite of god, dyd not ſpare his only begot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten ſone, but for vs all dyd beſtow hym vnto the moſt cruel death, that who ſo euer dooth beleue in hym ſhall not peryſh, but haue euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng lyfe.</p>
            <p>Therfore let vs loue hym agayne, and accordynglye honour hym for ſuch benefytes, as he moſt ryghtuoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly doth deſerue.</p>
            <p>What gretter loue can theyr be my
<pb facs="tcp:4378:17"/>
dere beloued childrn? If thou ſhuld<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt fall in a depe pete of water, &amp; a ſtranger comynge by draweth the out, Or If thou ſhuldyſt ly ſore ſyke at the poynt of death, that no mane ſhulde ſe any recouery in the, there cometh a phyſicion and reſtoreth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to health, thou culdeſte not ſhew no lyke kyndnes agayne correſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſuch pleaſures done to the. Much greatter pleaſures haue we recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of chriſt, which hath plucked vs out of the mouth of the deuyll, dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueryng vs from hell, and promyſed euerlaſtynge lyfe and Ioy with the Angelles. O dere chyld, ſay thus in thy mynde, I wyll neuer ſyne more, ſeynge that ſyne is ſuch a fowll and abhominable thynge. Yea and yf I were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrayned to ſynne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand deathes, yet wyll not I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent therto. Chriſte was the ſone of god, before heauen and earth was mad,
<pb facs="tcp:4378:17"/>
whyche at the time appointed of the father was made ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with out any infectyon of ſynne, and liued with vs i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earthe, And at laſt ſuffered for the ſynnes of al the worlde. Learne my chyldren pacyence: Chryſt dyd beare hys croſſe a pon hys owne backe, was knocked and ſcoffed, was ſcourged, and was crouned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thornes. Mortify your membres in tyme, leſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euill growe inward and at length breake forthe to your greate peryll and daunger, yt folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth in the crede. The thyrde day he roſe a gaine from death, aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vp. et. c. beare thys (you chyldren &amp; elders alſo) I do not mumble vp theſe wordes with out intellyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. They be golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wordes and worthy to be wrytten in all mens hartes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fyngar of god. Chryſt ys riſen agayn from death, and ſo ſhall we: doeſt thou doubt that thy body ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:4378:18"/>
ryſe agayne? Chryſt ſayth it which can not lye, he ſyttyth on the righte hande of the father, from thence he ſhall come to reuenge the wycked, and to reward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godli with heauen. All thynges are geuen hym in hys hand of the father. And though we yet here remayne in earth weyke &amp; brickle veſſels, yet do we tari &amp; loke fore ioyes to come, promyſed vs by chriſt. And to whom did he promyſe this? To ſuch as once knowyng the trueth, be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to lede a vertuous &amp; an honeſt lyfe, as do ſuffer in thys preſent worlde much aduerſyte, for who ſo euer intend to lyue godly in chryſt Ieſu muſt nedes ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. In ſo much the lord hath ſo premonyſhed vs, let vs be content what ſo euer happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what ſo euer ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſyte we ſuffer for the gloryfyeng of hys name. And yf thou were in ſeruyce with ſome myghtie lord or
<pb facs="tcp:4378:18"/>
prynce, it could not be choſen, but thou ſhuldyſt a byde many pereis, take much paynes, ſuſteine greate cold, for the optainyng and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of thy lyuyng. Than rather ſuſteyne you the ſeruyce of thy lorde god, and doubt not of thy rewarde, for he hym ſelfe hathe promyſed to rewarde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in his endleſſe kingdom. I beleue in the holy ghoſt. &amp;c. which dyd teach and now dothe teach all the faythfull the truyth that Chriſt preached vnto vs. The operatyon of hym is to make vs dyſpyſe the world with all hys concupyſcence. Yonglynges, here I admonyſh you, whan ſo euer ani yll thoughtes tari long in your mindes, be you certain it ys the deuyll that hath ſtyrred vp the fyer. Caſte hym out throughe prayer and almoſe dede. The good ſpryte dothe ingender in vs the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrans of eternall thinges and
<pb facs="tcp:4378:19"/>
that be good, And let not the thyng that is good, dwell in a corrupte place. If we be ſlacke &amp; neglygente now whan we be called of our mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull father to hys heauenly feaſt, he dothe but well and worthily, yf he call backe a gayne hys grace ſo ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilly of his mere te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dernes offered vnto vs. Truly we be well worthy of many ſcorgynges and betynges, if we return again to our old vices, after we haue receiued and knowen the grace. Your goyng is much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeable, your iagged &amp; cut apparell ſo daſſhyng a bout you, do declare a mad and a foolyſh mynde, you be proude and puffed vp, you gyue no reuerence to your elders. The holy goſt dyd not teache you thys, why do you neglecte hys inſpyratyon? feyght agaynſt ſathan with all his pompe and that with contynuall prayers. Reſyſt the vyces whiche
<pb facs="tcp:4378:19"/>
growe in you. Good chyldren, lerne to pray gladly our lordes prayer, ſo ſhall you proue to good men, and ſhall be bothe worſhyp to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wealth and an orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to chrſtyes relygion. Flee from ſuch company whoſe mynde is all ſet to doo myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheyfe, Theſe be wycked perſones, which go about al they can toppres the veryte, by their maneres, their counſels, and lyfe: how be it, they be not able to euerte, although thei ſumwhat obſcure it, but onli in ther owne hartes, which delyte in lyes. God is mercifull and very gentill, therfore call apon hym in chryſtes name. And dyſpiſe not the grace of god, after the faſſhyon of ſum yong men to foolyſhe and lyghte, whiche yll prouyd for them ſelues both heare &amp; in the world to come. But theſe flowers and life of theirs will ſone vade, &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall they perceiue
<pb facs="tcp:4378:20"/>
&amp; forthynke in their myndes, what thei haue doune. I beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> catholik churche et. c. There is but one faith of all that euer haue ben, bothe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and Apoſtelles, And thys vniuerſall churche is not conteined in one place here, but in all places of the world chryſtes church is dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ꝑſed. be you not deceiued ſo to think chriſtes church only to be, whych is gouerned vnder the wycked pope. The lorde hath hys people in euery place. The true church is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche hath the worde of god, the olde and new teſtament, whiche hathe here ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, baptyme, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords bread. Yf any thynge be taught the a gaynſte the ryght doctryne of the goſpell by any man how holi ſo euer he be, be it to the accurſed. Yf the papyſtes do teach the true honor, worſhyp, and dygnyte of chryſte. folow and embrace that doctryne.
<pb facs="tcp:4378:20"/>
But elles yf they teach any other thynge, that is their owne dremes and traditions, a voyde yt quickly, leſte you bee defyled with the leuen therof. And be not quick i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleuing them that ſay. Our forefatheres, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſhops with all the generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles, gathered to gether in the holi ghoſt, haue appoynted this (though yt be dyrectly agaynſte the worde of god) therfore you muſt beleue it vnder payne of eternall damnation Let them auaunte with their bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage and phantaſyes, wherewith they haue infectted and deluded all the world ſo long. Let the youth learne the worde of god exactly, ſo ſhall they eaſely iudge of the faythe and worde of god, and ſhall not lyghtly ſwarue from goddes ryght doctrine. The ſhepe of Chryſt heare and perceyue hys voyce and folowe hym whyther ſo euer he goyth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4378:21"/>The forgiuenes of ſinnes. &amp;c. Som herytyckes there haue bene whiche haue denyed forgyuenes of ſynnes, and haue inuented I can not tell what peſtylent doctryne out of ther owne heades. Alſo let theſe a voyed with there errors. Chriſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyth ſynners to hym dayly, A men dement of lyfe is preached to all men for them to obtaine forgiuenes of theyre ſynnes. Troble not your ſelues a bout aurycular confeſſyon. To the lorde confeſſe your ſynnes euery day and hower, the whyche he only forgeueth hym ſelfe.</p>
            <p>you fathers haue reſpecte and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of your ſeruantes &amp; maides, that they run not all the yeare long in theyre fylthines with out feare of god. And ſo doynge you ſhall be lightly alowed of god. let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> learne ſermones early out of the worde of god, wher by they ſhall learne to
<pb facs="tcp:4378:21"/>
know god, which is the begynning of an honeſt lyfe: forgyue you all enuye and all harered. And your father in heauen ſhall forgiue your offences. We haue remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſyns, where? In the croſſe, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as chriſt ſuffered for all our ſynnes, that is, the ſynnes of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. Thynke ye not there ſynnes to be pardoned, which lyue in all wyckednes and fylthynes. God forbid that we ſhuld ſaye ſuch mene beleue in chriſt that haue theyre hartes full of filthenes and replenyſhed with all miſcheffe. And let no man thynke yt muche, thoughe he ſuffer here ſum kynde of croſſe in thys world for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſtyce &amp; glory of god, we haue a promyſe, of reyſyng of our fleſh, wherof the faythfull ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothyng doubteth, but is ſuer, (in nothyng more) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is an other lyfe after thys much bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter and iyofull. Thys is oure fayth
<pb facs="tcp:4378:22"/>
which is taught vs from our youth and which all chriſten men do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe. Nether do we teach any other what ſo euer papiſtes bable of vs. yf this fayth be lyuely in vs, it wyll brynge forth fruytes accordyngly, What doth baptiſme make, it clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs in this maner from ſynnes. And lyke as the water purgeth the body, ſo doth the word of god purge the ſoule. Let vs abhorre &amp; renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce our fylthy and ſynfull lyfe, yf we be chriſten men in dede as we profeſſe. Howbeit yet the appetite, &amp; proneſſe to ſynne, remayneth in vs ſtyll, the which yf we truſt in the lorde, is pardoned and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a way throughe grace. Our prayer with all deſier, that the glory of our Lorde may go forward, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his kyngdom daily may be enlarged vnto all the endes of the earth, wyl they nyll they theſe wicked papiſtes. Let our ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:4378:22"/>
and prayer be to god after hys wyll &amp; pleaſure, which ſtandyth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, &amp; profitable to vs warde: Say, O moſt holy father helpe our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytees, forgyue our manifold offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Gyue vs right faith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be applyaunt to all good workes which your wyll requireth. Deliuer vs from euill, that is, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuill that he haue no power nor impery vpon vs. Exerciſe your ſelues much in the lordes prayer, Put a waye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bokes of your wicked praiers wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, all the world is full. And be not like the hypocrytes whiche haue a greate pleaſure to bragge theyre prayers before other men, whyche alſo ſtand i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery corner of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtretes that they may be ſene of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but theſe haue theyr rewarde alredy, let them loke for none of god. Mat. vi, It is tyme I think now to draw to a concluſyon, ſeyng the hower is
<pb facs="tcp:4378:23"/>
full vp. I beſeche and deſire you fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by our Lorde Ieſus chryſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you gyue good chrſtiane example in your houſes to your chyldren and ſeruantes. Proue you exammynie wel your hartes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng to receiue the ſacramentes. If you fynd thys in your ſelues that ye can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente to leade a chryſten lyfe here after, ye may bouldly com, yf not, a way leſte ye be gyllty of the bodi &amp; bloode of the lorde. Or yf you do pourpoſe as you be wont to do after the feaſt of eaſter to ronne from towne to towne, lyke madde men, to fall a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayne to your olde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions, ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketynge with your hores, and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your harlots, I do you to wytte, you receyue yt to your damnatyon. Thou that arte a father inſtantly call vpon thy ſonne or thy ſeruant y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he come not hither to dyſhoneſt the borde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, or to receyue to him
<pb facs="tcp:4378:23"/>
his owne iudgment, as paule ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. It is not one dayes buſynes, all our life time we ought to emploi thys matter. We wyll not, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papyſtes maner, our geſtes come to thys chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feaſte Let the papiſtis goe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their erores. It is no lyght thyng to receyue the body and blood of our lorde, here lyeth the weyght of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld hereafter lede a new lyfe, forſakyng our olde ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>full nature. Let all things ſpring of a faith vnfained, ſo al ſhalbe well both here and in the world to come, we ſhall bothe pleaſe men and all the Aungelles aboue, for they doo greattli embrace ſuch as theiſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hore god ſincereli, if we wold folow thys rule of charite, that we wolde loue our neighbour, as our ſelues &amp; pray for all our enemyes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold god haue greate delyte in vs.</p>
            <p>Nether let vs thynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chryſten
<pb facs="tcp:4378:24"/>
lyfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in wordes only, but in workes and dedes, other els do we nothyng but ſclaunder the name of chryſt amonge infydeles. The lord lyghten all our myndes with hys grace, that we may do all thynges to his glory. And to the edyfyenge of hys Catholike church. So be yt</p>
            <trailer>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>FINIS<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by me Humfrey Powell, dwellyng aboue Holburne conduit.</p>
            <p>And are to be ſould by Hugh Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleton, dwellyng at the ſygne of Saynt Auguſtine, in Poules church yarde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4378:24"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
